A Finding Aid to the Lucile Blanch papers, circa 1898-1963, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Lucile Blanch papers
circa 1898-1963
Archives of American Art
Blanch, Lucile, 1895-1981
AAA.blanluci
Archival Resource Key
0.5 Linear feet
The papers of painter Lucile Blanch (1895-1981) measure 0.5 linear feet and date from circa 1898 to 1963. The scattered papers comment on Blanch's relationships with her husband Arnold Blanch, her sister Beatrice Lundquist, and fellow artists. Found are biographical material, correspondence, a diary fragment by Beatrice Lundquist, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter Lucile Blanch (1895-1981) measure 0.5 linear feet and date from circa 1898 to 1963. The scattered papers comment on Blanch's relationships with her husband Arnold Blanch, her sister Beatrice Lundquist, and fellow artists. Found are biographical material, correspondence, a diary fragment by Beatrice Lundquist, and photographs.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reel 1003 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Biographical / Historical
Minnesota and New York etcher and painter Lucile Blanch (1895-1981) helped to establish the Woodstock Art Colony in Woodstock, New York.
Born Lucile Lundquist in rural northern Minnesota, she studied at the Minneapolis School of Art where she met her future husband, Arnold Blanch. They moved to New York City where Lucile studied at the Art Students League. Lundquist was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in the mid-1930s and participated in the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Project, creating several murals for public buildings, before teaching art classes.
Lucile Blanch died in Georgia in 1981 and is buried in Woodstock, New York.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials on reel 1033 were lent for microfilming in 1975 by Lucile Blanch and the correspondence on frames 297-410 was subsequently donated in 1976 by Blanch. Additional correspondence, photographs and a sketch were donated in 2021 and 2023 by Nancy Lundquist, a relative of Lucile Blanch.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming on reel 1003 including a sketchbook; 46 drawings, prints and reproductions of Blanch's work; illustrations from W. H. Hudson's Green Mansions; 3 scrapbooks containing clippings, reproductions of her work, exhibition material, photographs, and letters; and miscellaneous printed material. Loaned materials were returned to the donor and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Painters -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Etchers -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Women artists; Women painters; Women printmakers; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Drawings
- Lucile Blanch Papers, circa 1898-1963; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include a sketch of cats by Blanch sent to her sister Beatrice and two writings. An untitled writing concerns art and another is a supplemental narrative for Blanch's application for a Guggenheim Fellowship.
  Lucile Blanch's correspondence includes letters to her sister Beatrice, as well as letters from fellow artists and friends. Notable correspondents include Edward Bruce, Stuart Edie Carson, Ernst Fiene, Ray Harris, Frida Khalo, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Barbara Morgan, Diego Rivera, Eleanor Rixson, Dorothy Varian, and Forbes Watson. Many letters concern Blanch's application to the Guggenheim Fellowship. Blanch's letters to Beatrice Lundquist and her family are detailed and personal. Many letters describe her current artworks, memories, travel, and the art business run by Blanch and her husband Arnold. Blanch discusses visits with other artists and her own feelings of inadequacy. Additional letters are from school-aged children thanking Blanch for a lecture.
  Arnold Blanch's correspondence is from Alexander Brook, Adolf Dehn, Reginald Marsh, Frank Rehn, and Katherine Schmidt. Letters from Beatrice Lunquist are to her sister and other members of their family. Scattered family letters are from Blanch's mother and brother.
  A diary fragment by Beatrice Lundquist is labeled as her last diary and was kept immediately prior to her death.
  Photographs include infant and childhood portraits of Lucile Blache, Beatrice Lundquist, and other members of the Lunquist family. Later snapshots were taken of Lucile and Beatrice in New Hope, Pennsylvania, and on various vacations. Additional photographs are of Beatrice throughout her life, and may include modeling photos.
  - Biographical Material, 1925-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material, Oversized, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Correspondence, Blanch, Arnold, 1932-circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Blanch, Lucile, 1926-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Blanch, Lucile, to Beatrice Lundquist, 1926-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Lundquist, Beatrice, 1922-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Family, circa 1926-circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diary, circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, circa 1898-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)